## Joel Worrall

717.385.9970 / joel@joelworrall.com / @tangollama

# Innovation, Strategic Leadership, Digital Transformation, Product & Brand Development, Executive Management

## Summary

I started my career in the software industry as a programmer, architect, and consultant. More than a decade ago, I began growing my skills in the areas of people management, organizational leadership, strategic planning, brand development, product management, and enabling business transformation.

Today, I'm equipped with a service-oriented management philosophy, a strategic execution track record, and a passion for building great technology and great teams. My goal is to join a leadership team with a mission I can embrace, a culture I can influence, and a vision I can help shape.

## Skills

- Technology product development, including hands-on software engineering and architecture
- Management of departments across distributed offices, time zones, and continents
- Team leadership, mentoring staff and subordinates, managing up, and coaching peers
- Brand and product positioning as well as internal and external messaging
- Marketing and fundraising, including proposal creation and presentation
- Strategic planning and execution with sustainable results
- Corporate culture leadership, embracing and setting pace for core values
- Personnel management, including restructuring organizational reporting relationships
- Talent identification, recruitment, and onboarding
- Volunteer recruitment and management, including open source software contributors
- Strong presentation, public speaking, and written communication skills
- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Multi-million dollar budget management
- Seven years of Board-level reporting experience
- Classroom management and curriculum creation in a higher education setting

## **Education & Training**

Bachelor's in Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA (2000) Master's in Religion, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA (2015) The Marketing Seminar with Seth Godin, <a href="https://themarketingseminar.com">https://themarketingseminar.com</a> (2017)

## Presentations & Talks

See videos of several of my public talks and presentations at <u>ioelworrall.com/talks</u>.

## Experience

## Stripe (January 2021 to present)

In 2021, I joined the leadership team of the Product and Partner Platform organization at Stripe in a role as a Technical Advisor to the head of the organization. Three weeks into my tenure, I was asked to take over the Experience Platform organization, the teams responsible for the frontend programming model and platform services for dashboard.stripe.com as well as design systems that power other frontend Stripe experiences.

## Head of Engineering, Experience Platform – January 2021 - Present

- Manager-of-managers for Stripe's Dashboard interface, all levels of the unified, frontend programming model, component library, GraphQL layer, runtime services, and messaging
- Leading numerous multi-team, cross-org initiatives on reliability, performance, and architecture as Stripe's services expand into a multi-product, multi-region suite of financial services
- Diversifying the remote employee profile to include multiple time zones and continents as we seek to attract underrepresented demographics and best talent across the US and world

Primary technologies / tools: React, HTML/CSS/JS, GraphQL, Ruby, OpenTelemetry

## New Relic (+2.5 years)

New Relic is the industry leader in monitoring the modern cloudstack, adding over two trillion events and metrics per day to their real-time analysis platform while serving over 17,000 customers (including more than half the Fortune 100). Operating at the intersection of product and go-to-market, my roles provided strategic leadership and execution, often resulting in open source code.

#### Senior Director, Open Source - October 2020 - January 2021

- Part of the executive product leadership team, reporting to the Chief Product Officer
- Lead the cross-team development of the platform's deployment and onboarding architecture
- Oversaw the open source program office

#### <u>Director, Open Source and Developer Advocacy</u> – October 2019 - October 2020

- Hybrid product manager / engineering manager / architect while (by choice) still writing code
- Served in a primary support role to the GM of Developer Ecosystem
- Responsible for our developer advocacy content, event strategy, and developer programs
- Drove the establishment of our open source program office, strategy, and GM roadmaps

#### <u>Director, Programmability</u> – May 2019 - October 2019

- Lead the New Relic Labs team within our Services organization
- Represent customer platform needs to the Product teams in Portland and Barcelona
- Support the GM of New Relic One regarding programmable feature definition

#### Principal Extensibility Architect - May 2018 to May 2019

- Built early-stage customer solutions using GraphQL, React, and cloud services
- Helped deliver, shape, and support New Relic's Developer Program
- Championed the goals of the founder/CEO with regards to platform programmability

Primary technologies / tools: React, Node.js, HTML/CSS/JS, GraphQL, New Relic, GitHub, AWS

## Masterworks (10 months)

Re-platformed a 30-year-old agency that was focused on serving faith-based organizations in the rescue and relief sectors. In my role, I helped to reengineer the agency while simultaneously bringing digital products to market.

#### Vice President, Chief Technologist – August 2017 to May 2018

- Created a data service to aggregate constituent data across a myriad of platforms and tools to create a unified understanding of donor response as well as automation models
- Reshaped technology and digital delivery processes to follow industry best practices
- Built the staffing capabilities of the agency with regards to technology and digital marketing
- Vetted and implementing outsourcing and partner relationships
- Led platform and partner selection for technology-related systems and solutions

Primary technologies / tools: Google BigQuery, Looker, Piwik Pro, React, Node.js, PHP, Symfony, MySQL, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Pantheon, WPEngine, Salesforce.com, Google Apps

## Messiah College (2 years)

In my first, professional teaching engagement, I taught an introductory web technologies course in Spring 2018 followed by a two-semester senior capstone course in system analysis, design, and implementation. I've recently chosen to reduce my role to guest lecturer in Computer Science.

Adjunct Instructor - February 2018 to May 2019

## CURE International (7.5 years)

Member of the executive leadership team, head of technology, marketing, and CURE's innovative online donor reporting platform (<u>CUREkids</u>), providing oversight and strategic direction to a global charitable healthcare organization with 1,600 employees and an operational presence in 29 countries.

Chief Technology Officer and Office of the CEO – June 2016 to May 2017

<u>Chief Technology Officer</u> – May 2014 to June 2016

Vice President of Technology and Marketing – July 2010 to May 2014

<u>Vice President of Technology</u> – October 2009 to July 2010

- Oversaw all technology, marketing, brand-building and creative efforts
- Served as the lead executive and primary communicator through a CEO transition
- Architected and co-founded the award-winning <u>cure.org</u> and the <u>CUREkids</u> platform
- Co-founded the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source software project
- Led transition from traditional nonprofit software tools to a full cloud technology strategy
- Wrote and spoke for conferences and events across a variety of audiences and venues
- Conducted executive recruiting and management
- Directed crisis communications and public relations
- Directed the creation of CURE's content marketing strategy
- Oversaw the growth of CURE's first, successful monthly recurring revenue program
- Led the messaging and execution for CURE's largest annual fundraising event (\$6M)

Primary technologies / tools: PHP, MySQL, jQuery, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Salesforce.com, Google Apps, Mailchimp, Stripe, Hubspot, DigitalOcean, Rackspace

## Mzinga & KnowledgePlanet Inc. (3.5 years)

Led a 75-person engineering department of a venture-backed enterprise software company. Responsible for technology roadmap, product development, acquisition due diligence, and R&D.

Vice President, Engineering & Development – March 2009 to October 2009

<u>Director of Engineering</u> – August 2008 to March 2009

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008

Development Manager - Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

Software Architect – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

- Led shift of product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete Software as a Service multi-tenant, single instance environment
- Provided technical leadership through a debt restructuring and recapitalization event
- Guided the engineering through the merger of three companies including offshore teams
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services
- Performed technical diligence through acquisitions
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships

Primary technologies / tools: Java, HTML/CSS/JS, Oracle, SVN, CVS, FogBugz

## (Volunteer) HospitalRun (4.5 years)

Co-founder of the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source health information platform, responsible for strategic direction, community management, messaging, code contributions, and reviewing pull requests.

<u>Core Team [Volunteer]</u> – February 2014 to July 2018

Primary technologies / tools: Node, Ember, CouchDB, PouchDB, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic

## Java Brewery, Inc (3 years)

Outsourced system architecture, software development, and interim engineering management.

Sole Proprietor and Senior Consultant – April 2003 to June 2006

- Engaged in outsourced product development, management, market research, and leadership
- Served as technical liaison and interim engineer for multiple organizations
- Analysis of company models, architecture, requirements, design and implementation services
- Architected the content management tools for Comcast

Primary technologies / tools: Java, MySQL, Postgres, CVS, SVN

## CommNav Inc. (3 years)

Lead Java developer of a 20-person startup focused on a business portal framework.

<u>Lead Architect</u> – July 2000 to April 2003

## Knowledgeplanet Inc. (1 year)

Entry-level developer that quickly took over leadership in an existing and more senior team.

Software Engineer – May 1999 to June 2000